John Lawrence papers, Inclusive Dates: 1955-2000, undated, Bulk Dates: 1968-1986.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
John Lawrence papers
Inclusive Dates: 1955-2000, undated, Bulk Dates: 1968-1986.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
68
Keston Institute, 1969 -
3 document boxes
The John Lawrence Papers primarily contain journals detailing Lawrence’s trips. These journals focus on living situations and church-state relations in those countries. Also included are a few documents related to Frontier.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
John Waldemar Lawrence was born in 1907. He was a member of the renowned Lawrence family who held powerful positions in India during the British occupation. Sir John Lawrence was a direct descendent of the family of Lucknow Lawrences who entered the baronetage in 1858 through the appointment of Sir Henry Montgomery Lawrence’s son. Sir John Lawrence was the sixth baronet of his family. In 1948, he married Jacynth Ellerton, who died in 1987, and in 1988, he married Audrey Woodiwiss. Sir John Lawrence died on December 30, 1999.
Sir John Lawrence’s career was marked by involvement with various publications. During World War II, he helped create Britansky Soyuznik (British Ally) which was “the only uncensored official [newspaper] publication to be produced in the Soviet Union” (Bourdeaux). In the 1950s, Sir John created and edited Frontier, a Christian periodical which discussed the popular questions and themes of the day. In 1969, he and Michael Bourdeaux founded Keston, which produced Religion in Communist Lands. Sir John Lawrence held the roles of chairman and president successively at Keston. He also wrote several books, including A History of Russia, Russians Observed, The Hammer and the Cross, The Journals of Honoria Lawrence, and Lawrence of Lucknow.
As evidenced by journals in the collection, Sir John Lawrence was an important leader in the 20th century religious community and helped promote freedom of religion through co-founding of Keston. He was clearly a Christian leader, as he was involved in some proceedings of the Second Vatican Council and was often invited to important ecumenical meetings and Christian conferences as a representative of the Anglican Church.
Sir John Lawrence lived in London, he travelled extensively because of his involvement with many organizations, invitations to ecumenical events, and tours. During these international trips, he wrote journals which he sent to various supporters and friends. These documents provide great details of countries and events as well as offering insight into Lawrence’s personality, beliefs, relationships, health, and life. Michael Bourdeaux wrote about these journals, “He left a series of diaries for his confidants, recording his extensive travels and encounters with atheists, humble clerics and senior prelates. These were too colourful and honest about the hundreds of church leaders Lawrence met to see print during his lifetime - or possibly theirs - but the material for a great book is preserved and ready to provide a rich source for his literary executor.”
Scope and Content
The John Lawrence Papers contain materials related to his writing, including, journals, correspondence, letters, manuscripts, clippings, Frontier, lists, pamphlets, a newspaper article, and a postcard. The content spans from 1955 to 2000, with the bulk focusing on the early 1970s and mid-1980s. The most common subjects include, but are not limited to, Frontier, Keston, religious activity, Jews, icons, the KGB, GB-USSR Association, Customs, churches converted to museums, Britansky Soyuznik, Friendship House, Religion in Communist Lands, History of Russia, news sources in the Soviet Union, persecution, the Lawrence family, Lawrence’s health, ecumenism, Mount Athos monks, Mount Athos monasteries, race relations, and lifestyle. The most prominent individuals listed in the collection are Michael Bourdeaux, Stalin, Solzhenitsyn, Teilhard de Chardin, Ray Oppenheim, Fr. Job, Fr. Shpiller, Metropolitan Nikodim, Bishop Pitirim, Metropolitan Anthony, Fr. David, Metropolitan Philaret, Jacynth Ellerton Lawrence, Xenia Dennen; John Roberts, Fr. Alexander, and Fr. Ilian. The majority of the content focuses on the Soviet Union, India, and Mount Athos.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the John Lawrence Papers arranged by topic. These have been organized by date and placed into new folders. A few extra journals from the Mount Athos series were placed in corresponding folders within the Journal series. The overall structure of the collection has been maintained.
The John Lawrence Papers are arranged into two series: I. Correspondence and II. Literary Works
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 68.
Related Resources
Related references
Bourdeaux, Michael. “Sir John Lawrence: Diplomatic Dealings with Russia, India and the Church of England.” The Guardian. February 1, 2000. Accessed March 30, 2022.
Rayment, Leigh. “Baronetage.” June 2, 2018. Accessed April 1, 2022.
“Voices of the Voiceless: Commemorating Keston’s 50th Anniversary.” Keston Collection Exhibits, January 13, 2020. Accessed April 1, 2022.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Places
India -- Description and travel.; Soviet Union -- Description and travel.
Subjects
Church and state -- Soviet Union.; Communism and Christianity -- Soviet Union.; Monasteries -- Greece -- Athos.; Postcards.
Genres
Articles.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Travel writing.
- Correspondence, 1976-1985, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series primarily contains letters from monks on Mt. Athos in Greece. The majority of the letters were written by Fr. Job, and the two most referenced monasteries appear to be the Skete of Prophet Elias and St. Panteleimon.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 68.
  - Correspondence: Mt. Athos (1 of 3), 1978, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Mt. Athos (2 of 3), 1984-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Mt. Athos (3 of 3), 1982, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Literary Works, 1955-2000, undated; 2
  This series contains a variety of documents, including travel journals, Frontier booklets, Frontier documents, and a few manuscripts. The travel journals detail the experiences of Sir John Lawrence on many of his international trips. These trips were often taken to attend conferences, religious group meetings, or were in association with travel agencies (particularly Swan Tours). The most common destinations were the Soviet Union and India. The journals detail the people, church life, and overall experiences in the country.
  - Frontier: Christian News-Letter: Publications, 1955 April-1956 July (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Frontier: Christian News-Letter: Conference Materials: Manuscripts, Correspondence, circa 1963, circa 1964, circa 1965, circa 1966, 1967 March and July (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General: Manuscripts, 1984 November, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Russia in My Life": Manuscript, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: Journey Notes, 1958 May-June (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Travel Journal: "Turkestan Travel", 1963 April-May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travel Journal: Italy: "Observatori Romano": Fourth Session of the Second Vatican Council, 1965 October-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Travel Journal: "African Excursion", circa 1966 July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Travel Journal: Sri Lanka: "Ceylon Safari", 1967 May-June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Travel Journal: Czechoslovakia: "Spring in Prague", 1968 March-April (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Travel Journal: Romania: "Romanian Record", 1968 May-June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Russia Revisited" (1 of 2), 1968 August (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Russia Revisited" (2 of 2), 1968 September (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Moscow 1970", 1970 September (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Travel Journal: Denmark: "A Danish Diary", 1971 April-May (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Travel Journal: USA and Canada: "Methodists Observed": Twelfth World Methodist Conference, 1971 August-September (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Travel Journal: Ireland: "Last Diary of 1971", 1971 December (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Travel Journal: Ireland: "St. Patrick's Day", 1972 March (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Swanning in Muscovy", 1972 June (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: Soviet Union: "In the Bleak Midwinter", 1972 November-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Northern Lights", 1973 March (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Travel Journal: Switzerland: "Angels' Mount": Consolidation of Peace in Europe, 1973 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Travel Journal: Eastern Germany: "Beyond the Limit", 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Travel Journal: South Africa: "Southern Cross", 1974 February-April (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Three Men in a Delegation", 1974 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "The Spirit of Dilijan", 1974 September (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Travel Journal: Canada and USA: "Canadian Excursion", 1974 October-November (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Once More into the Breach", 1975 January-February (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Swanning the Caucasus and Turkestan", 1975 June (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union. "Moscow, the Caucasus and Turkestan", 1976 May-June (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Travel Journal: Greece: "To the Holy Mountain", 1976 September-October (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Leningrad, Moscow, Kiev 1977", 1977 March (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "A Journey Without Official Duties", 1978 September-October (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Travel Journal: India and Ceylon: "An Unscheduled Journey to India", 1978 November-December (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Travel Journal: India: "Subcontinental Journey 1979", 1979 September-October (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "White Lights", 1980 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Travel Journal: Greece: "To Be a Hagiorite", 1981 May-June (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Retreat to Moscow" (1 of 2), 1982 August-September (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Retreat to Moscow" (2 of 2), 1982 August-September (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Travel Journal: Greece: "Epitre de Saloniciens", 1982 October (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Forty Years On", 1983 May-June (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Provincial Russia": Yaroslavl, 1983 June (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "Old Wooden Russia (Staraia dereviannaia Rus')", 1984 August (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Travel Journal: Egypt: "Iter Sinaiticum", 1985 January (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Travel Journal: Soviet Union: "A Slightly Sentimental Journey": Moscow, 1985 December (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Travel Journal: Pakistan: "With the Piffers", 1986 April (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Travel Journal: Russia: "Fifty Years On", 1993 August (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Travel Journal: "Russia Again", 1994 July-August (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Travel Journal: Correspondence and Mailing Lists (1 of 2), 1978-1979, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Travel Journal: Correspondence and Mailing Lists (2 of 2), 1984-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Travel Journal: Records History, 2000 July (Box 3, Folder 15)